<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd">
    <record id="00041712" dt="2018-09-06">
        <version>5.2</version>
        <date value="2016-11-16" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/>
        <date_nonpreferred_format>Unknown Date</date_nonpreferred_format>
        <cms_record_id/>
        <title>Stanley_Janine</title>
        <accession/>
        <duration/>
        <collection_id>Bicentennial Oral History Project</collection_id>
        <collection_name>This interview was conducted as part of the Indiana University Bicentennial
            Oral History Project. The project is collecting interviews of IU alumni, staff, and
            faculty from all IU campuses in an effort to record the people's history of Indiana
            University.</collection_name>
        <series_id>IU Kokomo</series_id>
        <series_name/>
        <repository>Indiana University Library</repository>
        <funding>The Bicentennial Oral History Project is funded through the Indiana University
            Bicentennial.</funding>
        <repository_url/>
        <interviewer>Jessica Gordon</interviewer>
        <file_name/>
        <sync>1:|15(9)|29(1)|41(17)|48(12)|55(17)|77(7)|88(2)|113(8)|140(2)|186(16)|204(14)|218(10)|232(13)|247(6)|261(16)|277(12)|313(6)|334(6)|344(2)|352(6)|376(3)|391(15)|404(3)|436(2)|489(5)</sync>
        <sync_alt/>
        <transcript_alt_lang/>
        <translate>0</translate>
        <media_id/>
        <media_url>http://dlib.indiana.edu/OHMS/IU_Kokomo/Stanley_Janine.mp3</media_url>
        <mediafile>
            <host>Other</host>
            <avalon_target_domain/>
            <host_account_id/>
            <host_player_id/>
            <host_clip_id/>
            <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
        </mediafile>
        <kembed/>
        <language>English</language>
        <user_notes/>
        <index/>
        <type/>
        <description>Janine Stanley was interviewed by Jessica Gordon as part of the Bicentennial
            Oral History Project. At the time of the interview, Stanley had been employed as a
            librarian at IU Kokomo for 32 years. She describes her role in the libraries, and talks
            about the changes she's observed both in the library and to the campus. </description>
        <rel/>
        <transcript> ﻿ JG: My name is Jessica Gordon. The date is November the 16, 2016, and this is
            an interview for the bicentennial project at IU. I&#039;m here with Janine Stanley, and
            I&#039;m going to ask her some questions now. Janine, can you tell me where you were
            born and a little bit about your family background? JS: I was born in a small town of
            about 3,800 in Bremen, Indiana, northern Indiana. It has grown in population at the
            time. There&#039;s a lot of Hispanics that have moved down from the South Bend area, so
            it has enlarged since I&#039;ve lived in there, or since I&#039;ve lived there. But
            it&#039;s a little tiny town on Route 6 between Plymouth and Nappanee and -- I prefer
            Kokomo, Indiana [laughs]. It was a nice town to grow up in. JG: Now can you tell me a
            little bit about your family history, if you want to talk about that? JS: I lived in --
            I grew up in a family of four, had a sister two years older than me. My mother was a
            schoolteacher. My father was a factory worker. My grandparents -- I don&#039;t remember
            my father&#039;s parents, but my mother&#039;s parents lived two blocks away from us.
            They were always close to us. They only lived, like I said, a block away from us, and
            they passed away when I was in high school. So they were a big part of our lives. JG:
            Can you tell me about your education? A little bit about that? JS: Well, I--at that
            time, we were -- were a one-car family back then. My mom being a schoolteacher, we lived
            four blocks from our school and we would walk to school with my mom. She was a fast
            walker; we&#039;d always hoof it to school as fast as we could go. We&#039;d sit in her
            room and finish our homework assignments. We would sometimes help grade school papers,
            and we&#039;d head for our classes. After class we&#039;d come to--or, after school
            we&#039;d come back to her room and clean the chalkboards and do our homework until my
            dad came and picked us up after work and took us home. Just a very easy life. Then when
            my sister and I graduated from school, both of us went to Ball State University. At that
            time, it seemed like there wasn&#039;t much choice of what to be other than a nurse or a
            schoolteacher or a two-year secretarial. I was very confused as to what I wanted to be,
            so I was in Future Nurses at the same time that I was in Future Teachers [laughs]. The
            both of us went into elementary teaching-- . My sister did become a teacher, and she
            taught for about 25 years but really never enjoyed it. That kind of put a negative --
            negative feeling toward it for me. I did substitute a while and didn&#039;t enjoy that
            at all. In fact, my husband picked me up at the end of the day and he saw the sorrow
            look on my face, and he asked me, &quot;Tell me what you really liked about it.&quot;
            And I said, &quot;When I saw you pull up in the parking lot&quot; [laughs]. JG:
            [Laughs]. JS: So I never had a full-time job in teaching. By the time I graduated, they
            really didn&#039;t need teachers. I married him the summer after I graduated, and we had
            to go where the job was necessary, where they needed him. JG: Is that what led you to
            Kokomo? Your husband&#039;s move? JS: Actually, he worked for the state. He was an audit
            examiner for the state of Indiana, and worked in Marion. Then an opening came in
            Lawrenceburg, Indiana, moved down there. Then he had -- his best friend&#039;s father
            called him and said they had an opening in the bank for an audit--for an accountant and
            said, &quot;Would you like to come to work with us?&quot; He jumped for that. He said,
            &quot;Yeah.&quot; So just as his parents retired to Arizona, because he was from Kokomo,
            they moved to Arizona and had just given us their piano and moved the piano down to
            southern Indiana. We had just gotten it tuned. We turned right around, moved the piano
            and us right back to Kokomo. We moved to Kokomo. So that&#039;s where we&#039;ve been
            since 1972. JG: What led you to look at IU for employment? Janine would like to say this
            off the record. --recording paused-- JG: [Recording resumes]. Okay Janine, can you tell
            me about your first job here at IU Kokomo? JS: Well, it&#039;s the first and only job I
            had. What it is, it&#039;s basically ordering and cataloging books is the big part of
            it, and a lot of other smaller things that I do. JG: Can you tell me your title? JS: The
            title has changed through the years. It used to be serials and acquisition assistant,
            and now it&#039;s technical services assistant. I also do the binding-- . I also do
            gifts and -- I think that&#039;s it. JG: How long have you been employed at IU? How long
            have you done this job? JS: 32 years. JG: That&#039;s a long time. What--why have you
            stayed? JS: Because the pay is pretty good [laughs]. The pay and the benefits are good.
            I mean, it&#039;s too good to give up. JG: Yeah. JS: I mean, they always talk about
            robust benefits, and they&#039;re right. I would recommend it. JG: How do you feel your
            relationship is with your coworkers? JS: [Laughs] I would say it&#039;s pretty good. JG:
            Can you tell me about your relationship with faculty, students, or administration? Do
            you interact on a really personal level, or are you more of a behind-the-scenes person?
            JS: I&#039;m more of the behind-the-scenes person. JG: Do you have any additional roles
            on campus? Do you serve on committees or volunteer? JS: [Gesture: negative response] JG:
            Nope? Okay. JS: I enjoy the behind-the-scenes. JG: What are some benefits of being
            service, support, or professional staff at IU? JS: Benefits of being-- JG: Professional
            staff at IU. What are some benefits of being part of the staff here? JS: Hmm [Long
            pause]. JG: This is difficult to answer because Janine mostly works behind-the-scenes,
            as she mentioned before. JS: Well, just, you know, I guess you get to know a lot of
            people-- . You get to go to, I mean, go to ball games and go to Bloomington. I like to
            do that. JG: What are some of the challenges, would you say? Are there any challenges?
            JS: -- Challenges in I suppose getting that -- budget challenges probably. JG: Okay.
            Have you found any challenges within your job here? As far as difficultly in
            communication or contacting other individuals? Relating to the work that you do behind
            the scenes, have there been any challenges? JS: -- Not for me personally, but I&#039;m
            sure other people have found challenges though. Again, getting -- getting money for
            books, that kind of materials, needing money for materials would be one, probably. JG:
            Okay. How have you seen IU change over time? Have you seen a difference in diversity?
            JS: Definitely, yeah. That used to not even be--come up, 20 years ago. JG: What are some
            things you&#039;d like to see the university change? And what do you think they do very
            well? JS: Well [laughs], I would personally like to -- and I voiced this on my exit
            interview -- that would like to not see them push so hard on -- what was it -- what was
            it I said? JG: Comfort zone? JS: Yeah. On pushing you, yeah, out of your comfort zone.
            There&#039;s -- because there&#039;s plenty of people that want to be out of their
            office and be out of their comfort zone. JG: Have you always been a behind-the-scenes
            person? Do you prefer to work behind-the-scenes? JS: Yes, yeah. JG: Okay. So in regards
            to that, what do you think that IU does very well? [Long Pause; recorder beeps] So what
            do you think IU does very well? JS: I think it plans events very well. JG: Okay. Who are
            the people who have impacted you most in your IU employment here? This can be when you
            first began your work in the library or when you first came to campus? Anyone who has
            impacted your work? JS: Well, I think -- one thing I think the students that I worked
            with, because watching the students from start to finish, you know, watching them
            change. JG: The patrons or the student assistants? JS: The student assistants. I mean,
            the student assistants that I worked with to begin with were about my age [laughs]. The
            student assistants now are old enough to be my grandchildren. JG: [Laughs]. JS: It seems
            weird. JG: What were facilities like on campus? JS: Oh, yeah, and when I--the facilities
            on campus at the time were an old library main building and the east building. I think
            that was it. JG: Have they changed over time other than just renovation? JS: Renovation,
            and we&#039;ve got new buildings. We&#039;ve added buildings. It&#039;s just a bigger
            campus. We&#039;ve added a dormitory, and heavens: added parking facilities and torn
            down a grocery [laughs]. JG: We&#039;ve definitely grown. JS: Yeah. JG: Can you tell me
            about an event -- either IU or national -- that you particularly remembered from your
            time here at IU? This could be an event in Bloomington as well if you&#039;ve gone to
            Blooming--since you said you&#039;ve gone to Bloomington a lot-- . Do you remember a
            baseball game or something like that? Just a memory that sticks out to you from some
            event that you&#039;ve gone to. JS: Oh! Well, I remember -- I remember it was an event
            -- [recording pauses]. I remember an event and I know Cheryl Currens was a part of it
            and don&#039;t remember what it was for. But she instigated it and one of the librarians
            and I went over. It was cornhole and croquet and some other things. We played it over by
            the Well House, and I remember what fun we had. We had a lot of laughs. I don&#039;t
            know whether it was just a physical fitness type thing or what, but we had a good time
            with that. JG: What does IU mean to you? JS: Well, to me it&#039;s a great game
            [laughs]. I mean, to me [laughs], it&#039;s a big name to me, mainly because my husband,
            he had two sisters that went to IU. They&#039;re big fans of IU. The whole family is-- .
            It&#039;s a big name, it really is. Anybody who is associated with it can be proud in
            any way whatsoever. You can be proud to work here. You can be proud to go to school
            there. Even though I&#039;m a Ball State graduate I&#039;m still proud to work here. My
            daughter graduated from Purdue, and every time I say I&#039;m proud to work for IU she
            goes, &quot;Mom!&quot; [Laughs]. JG: That&#039;s the way it is [laughs]. What was the
            academic environment like for women on campus? JS: Here? While I worked here? JG: Yes.
            Can you think of the ratio of male to female? JS: I really can&#039;t speak to that,
            really. JG: How has the community changed in your time here in Kokomo? You mentioned
            that IU had added different buildings and taken away a grocery store. So how have you
            seen the community change since you&#039;ve been employed here? JS: Hm-- . Well
            it&#039;s grown. I know that-- . I think it&#039;s changed for the better because I know
            we&#039;ve brought my mom to Kokomo-- --Interview Interrupted-- JG: Okay, the interview
            had to be stopped for a moment. So we&#039;re going to pick back up at the question of:
            &quot;How has the community changed in your time here?&quot; JS: Well, I can attest to
            the fact that there are more assisted livings here because my mom, we moved her here
            from Bremen. At the time we moved her here, I believe there were only two assisted
            livings, and now there are -- oh, boy. One, two, three, four, five, six. At least six
            that I can think of. I&#039;m sure there will be more. JG: How have you seen the
            community accept the amount of growing students here at IU Kokomo? JS: How do they
            accept the number of growing students? JG: Yes. JS: I would -- I don&#039;t know how
            they feel about it. I would think they would like it. JG: Mmhmm. JS: Yeah. JG: Okay. Is
            there anything else you&#039;d like to add about your time here at IU? JS: I know
            I&#039;ll always feel bittersweet when I drive down Washington Street and look over at
            it [laughs]. I&#039;ll always think, &quot;That&#039;s where I worked.&quot; I brought
            my grandkids here one time, on a Saturday. They wanted to see where Nana worked.
            It&#039;s always bittersweet. That&#039;s what I&#039;ll feel about it. JG: Now are you
            leaving exactly at 32 years? JS: Well, I started here in August of 1984. JG: And when
            exactly are you retiring? JS: My last day will be November 30, this year. JG:
            That&#039;s coming up quick. JS: Yeah. JG: Well, I&#039;m sure as much as you will miss
            IU, that IU will miss you. JS: Yeah. JG: I&#039;ve enjoyed doing this interview with you
            and I&#039;d just really like to thank you for your time. JS: Okay. JG: I appreciate the
            stories and the history that you&#039;re bringing. So thank you. JS: Well, Jessie has
            been one of my favorites. She&#039;s been a sweetie. JG: You&#039;re so sweet. Thanks. </transcript>
        <transcript_alt/>
        <rights>By mutual consent of Indiana University and interviewee, the interviewee has given
            Indiana University this recording for scholarly, educational, and promotional use. The
            interviewee has also granted Indiana University all rights the interviewee possesses in
            this recording, including all intellectual property rights. Indiana University has
            granted the interviewee the nonexclusive license to make and to authorize others to make
            any use the interviewee wishes of the content of this recording, and I</rights>
        <fmt>audio</fmt>
        <usage>This interview is available online on this database as part of the Bicentennial Oral
            History Project. A copy of this interview will be deposited in the University Archives
            at IU Bloomington, as well as the the appropriate regional campus archives, if
            applicable.</usage>
        <userestrict>0</userestrict>
        <xmllocation/>
        <xmlfilename/>
        <collection_link/>
        <series_link/>
    </record>
</ROOT>
