<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00088704" dt="2023-01-31"><version>5.4</version><date value="1989-04-18" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format>4/18/1989</date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Interview with Frank Britten, Bloomer, Wisconsin, 1989</title><accession>CVM003</accession><duration>01:01:01</duration><collection_id>CVM</collection_id><collection_name>Chippewa Valley Museum</collection_name><series_id>CVM003</series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Recollection Wisconsin</repository><funding>Digitization and access supported by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities.</funding><repository_url /><subject>Veterans</subject><subject>Oral history</subject><subject>World War I, 1914-1918--Personal narratives</subject><subject>Wood-carving</subject><subject>Depressions--1929</subject><keyword>World War I, 1914-1918</keyword><keyword>Navy</keyword><interviewee>Britten, Frank</interviewee><interviewer>Flemming, Joanne</interviewer><format>Audio cassette</format><file_name>https://whs.aviaryplatform.com/embed/media/173337</file_name><sync>1:|10(1)</sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>https://whs.aviaryplatform.com/embed/media/173337</media_url><mediafile><host>Aviary</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>audio</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language>eng</language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type>Sound</type><description>Frank Britten recounts experience of being a skilled woodcarver from the age of 10.  Speaks of serving in the Navy in World War I from enlistment in June, 1918 to discharge September, 1919 in France.  Discusses the hardships caused by the lack of medical or monetary support provided to World War I veterans.  Recalls working in a paper mill in Ladysmith, Wisconsin and farming in Island Lake, Wisconsin after returning from World War I.  

Frank Britten was born on January 30, 1900 and passed away on January 1, 1991.
https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/95444038/frank-britten</description><rel /><transcript>BRITTEN, FRANK

Interviewed on April 18, 1989, about his life and work before the Depression.
Interviewed by Joanne FlemmingAbstract on April 18, 1989, by Joanne FlemmingOn
this tape, Frank Britten, Bloomer, talks about his work and social life in
Ladysmith before his marriage in 1929, and his life as a farm manager in Island
Lake during the Depression. He talks about his woodcarving for which he was won
many awards.

Four boys from Frank&#039;s family left for service. Family moved from Ladysmith back
to Kaukauna area where it was originally from. After Frank came out of service
after World War I, he did not go home to live. Traveled around for a few years;
went to the Dakotas for the threshing. Wanted to see more of the world. Got job
in paper mill in Ladysmith; called the Menasha Woodenware because that company
owned it. Ladysmith was called Warner before 1900. M. J. Smith built dam and
mill; he married in 1900. Then name of town changed to Ladysmith. Pope and
Talbot own this mill in Ladysmith now.

Frank said he had been woodcarving for 75 years. His grandfather was a
woodcarver in Germany. Then boys went to trade school to learn a skill. At 17,
they were admitted to apprenticeships. They worked at the apprenticeships until
they were 21. At 21, they could go to work. His grandfather came to the United
States and carved statues for a Catholic church. He worked at that job for seven
years. For the first five years, he had to send half of what he earned back to Germany.

If he failed at that job, he could not get another as a woodcarver.

Frank said woodcarving was in his bloodline. His father did some. All little
boys carried jackknives in their pockets. Tried woodcarving first at ten or 12
years old.

Frank&#039;s reputation as a woodcarver is such that when he went to Mt. Senerio
College in Ladysmith to sign up for art classes, he was asked to teach.

His woodcarvings are in four foreign countries and in different states. There
are books that list his carvings. He has made the Seal of the United States, the
seal of the American President, the Seal of the State of Wisconsin, and the
American Legion Seal.

Sometimes he draws projects out on paper first. Animals he just whittles out. A
project under consideration: Budweiser beer wagon and team. Carves in pine and
basswood. Some are finished with paint.

Different schools of finishing: old school versus modern school. Old school does
finish work with knife. Modern school finishes as smoothly as glass with
sandpapers, etc.

Won a few trophies and ribbons. Story about son&#039;s horse trophies and ribbons.

In World War I, Frank went overseas with the Navy to France. He wasn&#039;t stationed
there. The ship he was on landed troops. Take two or three days to refuel.
Learned a weaving technique in Paris to make pillow tops. Bought thread and
frames to take lessons. Saw no action, but ships fired on a few times. Enlisted
for 18 months at 18 years old. Enlisted in June 1918 and discharged in 1919.
could enlist for four years or duration of war.

Problems with being discharged after WWI. Mix-up in names with pronunciation and
paperwork. Discharged out of New York. Men stationed in Virginia and New York
harbors. Taken down to a big building and stayed there two or three days. Waited
until name was called.

Flu of 1918. Did help carry out men in different camps who got flu. Helped carry
out stretchers. Camps in Virginia Beach, Virginia. Went from there to New
Jersey, then to New York.

Times not easy for dischargees after WWI. Jobs were not held for them. No
hospitalization, no relief. Had to go on breadlines. Veterans fought that
situation. Veterans&#039; Hospital in Minneapolis built in 1932. Veterans went from
1920 to 1932 without help. Some help from Red Cross in form of clothes for kids,
but no money food or money for 1932 was first year of change for veterans.
Veterans got bonus of $300. Got full $300 if kept bond for 20 years. If kept
three months, got one-third of that amount. Frank cashed his.

After WWI, Frank roamed country for a year or two. Then got job in Ladysmith as
millwright. Repaired machinery. Later got jobs in machine shops. Ran turning
lathe and welded. Finally made his home in Island Lake north of Bloomer.

In 1900, second class post office in New Auburn moved to Island Lake.
Discontinued in 1930. First man to deliver mail from three delivered on
horseback. His name was Jesse James; real name was John James Jr. Jesse was
nickname. Got first car in 1924 while working in Ladysmith. Chevy Roadster.
Brand new. Learned to drive in 1920 to 1922. Father had Ford. Went home to visit
family in Kaukauna. Sister Rose taught him to drive that Model-T. In 1920, not
everyone had cars. Roads were all dirt. Remember first concrete road from around
late 1920s to 1930. Only eight feet wide. Highway 8 had concrete. After 1930,
more people got cars. What Frank and his friends did for amusement in Ladysmith,
shot guns at birds while hunting. Ice skated in winter. Skates fitted on shoes.

Made own skis. Starts to describe how skis were made from plain lumber rather
than barrel staves. More on shaping and waxing skis.

Went to movies, silent movies. Serials run on Friday nights. Took in a couple
movies a month. More house parties. Dance, eat refreshments. mouth organs or
accordions for instruments.

Played Also banjoes. Dances: waltzes. In 1920s, the Charleston and the shimmy.

Also played the &quot;bones&quot; for music.

Changes in women&#039;s fashions. Jokes about fashions. Changes from hobble skirts to flappers.

Met wife at house party in Ladysmith. Played games like &quot;Post Office.&quot;

Boarded with family while working in paper mill. Had bedroom. Had meals with
family. Landlady packed lunches for him.

Married March 5, 1929.

Prohibition: brother-in-law made moonshine. Went to private homes and sat on
back porch. Lady came out and gave whiskey or beer.

Brother bought crystal set (early radio). Peg turned on crystal. Bought Atwater
Kent radio in 1928. Paid cash for it. Wages: started for 28 cents an hour. Went
up to 38 cents an hour. Board was $5 a week. In the winter, when the men hunted,
he took rabbits and fish to landlady. Also shot deer.

Landlady had two children. Frank helped with hoeing. She also had a big garden.
Landlady did canning. Frank and his wife lived in Ladysmith after their marriage
Plain little white house--two bedrooms, living room, kitchen, indoor water, but
no toilet. Electric lights. Wood stove in kitchen; wood heater in living room.
When he was younger, Frank worked summers in pea factory. Wife never worked
until they lived in California in the 1950s. When Crash of 1929 came, Frank was
working in paper mill. When men walked out, they got their paychecks and nothing
else. No unemployment. Mill shut down.

Started up several years later. Men who worked there could get old jobs back again.

Moved out around Island Lake. Businessman had farm and needed someone to run it
for him. Frank took job.

In Depression, Frank bartered for work. Farmer wanted second floor on house;
paid Frank half in money and half in meat.

Most people thought Hoover was a miser. Country was &quot;dry&quot; when FDR took office;
ended Prohibition. Saloons no longer called &quot;saloons&quot;, but taverns. Women could
go into them then.

Story about parents shopping on Friday evenings. Father went into saloon while
Mother got groceries. Frank got a small glass of beer. Different reforms FDR started.

Farms affected by Dust Bowl years. Hay crops so poor that owner had to buy hay
towards spring. Sold a few of cows. Price of cows dropped so, didn&#039;t know if
should sell them or buy hay and feed. Farm was 100 acres; 60 was cleared land.
16 cows. Frank had no farming experience before Island Lake but knew the could
do job. One cow sold for $16. Frank listened to FDR&#039;s &quot;Fireside Chats&quot; on radio.
Description of FDR&#039;s voice and personality. Talk about ancestors in Germany
before WWI. Frank was at a combination store/tavern buying gas for his car when
he heard about Pearl Harbor on the radio.

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights><fmt>audio</fmt><usage>Copyright to this resource is held by the Chippewa Valley Museum, Eau Claire, Wisconsin</usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation>https://ohms.recollectionwisconsin.org/render.php?cachefile=NEH_CVM003.xml</xmllocation><xmlfilename>NEH_CVM003.xml</xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>